## Mohamed Hachaichi (Ph.D)

Researcher with a strong background in linear algebra, statistics, science and programming.

[ Personal website ] . [ Twitter ] . [ LinkedIn ]. [ Google Scholar ] .

hachaichi\_mohamed@outlook.com . (+33) 635 549 103

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher at the Institute of Urbanism and Geography Alpes (IUGA) at Grenoble Aples University. I hold a Ph.D. in circular urban metabolism and climate change delivered by the laboratory of "Cities, Urbanism and Sustainable development" at the Polytechnic school of Architecture and Urbanism (Algiers-Algeria).

Currently interested in designing a rapid whole system change on a global scale using new relevant sustainability metrics in a data-driven approach coupled with Artificial Intelligence (AI) algorithms. I Aim to clearly identify social tipping points using behavioral mechanisms and pattern recognition to find structure in chaotic social/economic/urban environments.

### Academic referees

- Prof. Sebastien Bourdin: sbourdin@em-normandie.fr: Professor of Economic Geographiy at EM Normandy Business School, Economy, Territories & Sustainable Development Department (Caen, France)
- **Dr. Jafaru Egeiya:** jafaruegieya@gmail.com: Postdoctoral researcher at Stellenbosch University (Cape Town, South Africa)

## Experience

Post doctoral fellowship, Institue of Urbanism and Geography Alps (10/2022 - 10/2023, Grenoble, France)

- Territorial systems' resilience:
- Ecological metabolism is composed of two entries: (i) Input section includes water, raw materials inputs, and energy. (ii) Output includes carbon emissions (CO2), waste water, and solid wastes.
- Affluence flux.
- · Governance structure.

Assistant Researcher, EM Normandie Business School (11/2021 - 07/2022, Caen, France)

- Collecting, cleaning & harmonizing COVID-19-related data:
- Explaining the spatial diffusion of the COVID-19 across EU regions (spatial econometrics models).
- Explain why some regions were severely hit by the virus and others were not.

Center Manager, Stellenbosch University (2011 - 2012, Cape Twon, South Africa)

• CoT's WFE nexus model: a six-way perspective (compromising population, agriculture, water, energy, economy, and climate). The model uses a system dynamics framework. To predict water availability at the catchment areas, precipitation was predicted using 17 climate parameters through 3 climate

scenarios using a downscaling process of Global Climate Models (GCM), and then after we used the downscaled data into a PCNN model using a Transfer-Learning approach.

• Climate change - water scarcity - droughts

# **Teaching**

University lecturer, Institue of Urbanism and Geography Alps (03/2023 - 04/2023, Grenoble, France)

- Giving a series of lectuers at the department of urbanism of "Voirie et espace public"
- Creating excercices and correct them.
- Grading students

University teacher, Polytechnic School of Architecture and Urbanism (11/2021 - 07/2022, Algiers, Algeria)

- Teaching classes with 25 students, subject: 3D modulization using Revit and 3Dmax
- Prepare and correct exams
- Perform 3D modeling for complex buildings and shapes
- Participate in my lab work of Cities, urbanism, and Sustainable Development: accompany Master candidates, international conferences, writing papers.

### Education

Ph.D. diploma in Circular urban Metabolism and Climate Change (10/2016 - 03/2021)

- · Carbon carrying capacity
- Coursework in physics, engineering, and statistics.

MS.s diploma in Architecture and Urban Project (2008 - 2011)

Master's degree: A student level, (ranked 3ed out of 183 students).

### Intership

Potsdam Institute for climate impact research Research domain IV: Transdisciplinary Concepts & Methods

### Skills

**Programming:** Python, SQL, R, Fortran, git, HTML/CSS, Pytorch, TenserFlow **Mapping:** ArcGis, Qgis, Mapinfo (+ R & Python for spatial data science) **Graphic design:** Photoshop, Inkscape, InDesign, Illustrator

## Languages

- Amazigh: read, speak, write.
- Arabic: read, speak, write.
- French: read, speak, write.
- English: read, speak, write.
- Deutsch: read, speak, write.

# Side-Projects

#### \*Geosis (2022-present)

• A python package for advanced geographic analysis (geoparsing, network analysis, community detection, and spatial mapping).

#### \*Englighten (2022-present)

 An online podcast with researchers, politics, and practitionners across the globe. The main topics includes: Sustainability, Artificiel Intellegence, climate change, human-nature interations, and mankinf-machine nexus.

### **Publications**

- Hachaichi, M. (2023). Unpacking the urban virtual water of the Global South: Lessons from 181 cities.
   Ecological Economics, 210, 107859.
- Hachaichi, M. & Bourdin, S. (2023) "Wheels within wheels: Mapping the genealogy of circular economy using Machine Learning"
- Egieya, J. M.A. Amidu, Hachaichi, M. (2023) "Small modular reactors: An assessment of workforce requirements and operating costs"
- Hachaichi, M., & Egieya, J. (2023). "Water-Food-Energy Nexus in Global Cities: Addressing Complex Urban Interdependencies"
- Hachaichi, M. (2022). "Cities: Allocating climate change responsibilities at planetary scale"
- Hachaichi, M, (2022) -preprint-. "Reshaping modern urban models with the global environmental ceiling: What, When How, and Why?"
- Hachaichi, M. and Baouni, T., (2021). "Virtual carbon emissions in the big cities of middle-income countries". Urban Climate, 40, p.100986
- Mohamed H, Tahar B, (2020), "Downscaling the planetary boundaries (Pbs) to city scale-level: Derisking MENA region's environment future". Environmental and Sustainability Indicators, Elsevier
- Mohamed H, Jan K, Tahar B, (2020), "Evaluating city carbon Carrying capacity: How many people can Algiers support?". Algerian Journal of environmental science and technology
- Mohamed H, Tahar B, (2019), "The carbon footprint model as a plea for cities towards energy transition: The case of Algiers, Algeria". International Journal of Energy and Environmental Engineering

# Scientific reports (technical reports)

Territorial impacts of COVID-19 and policy answers in European regions and cities

### Scientific conferences

• International Colloquium, 2017, Batna-Algeria, Prefiguring and designing the architectural and urban landscape from the perspective of a sustainable quality of the city of the future of the Mediterranean

countries, "Carbon carrying capacity at the service of urban planning, the case of Algiers urban ecosystem".

- International Colloquium, 2017, Batna-Algeria, Prefiguring and designing the architectural and urban landscape from the perspective of a sustainable quality of the city of the future of the Mediterranean countries, "Resilient landscape for man and nature, the case of the Bainem-Algiers forest ecosystem".
- International Colloquium, 2019, Rome-Italy, Green Urbanism III, "Algiers urban model from vulnerability to resiliency: Shifting the development patterns using the carbon footprint model".
- Global Conference on Economic Geography (GCOEG), Machine Learning Meets Economic Geography: Alternative Data and Methods for Mapping and Analysing Geographies of Knowledge Production and Knowledge Relations, 2022, Dublin-Ireland, "Wheels within wheels, tracking the gleam of the circular economy using machine learning".
- 5th international conference on technologies & business models for circular economy, 2022,
   University of Maribor Press, "Urban Water-Food-Energy Interdependences: Solving Urban Challenges
   Together", Mohamed Hachaichi, Jafaru Musa Egieya, Neill Goosen.
- Dimitrie Cantemir International Geographical Conference ESPON TERRCOV Workshop, 2022, Iasi-Romania, "The spread of the COVID-19 pandemic in Europe changing spatiotemporal patterns of pandemic indicators". Andris Igari, Mohamed Hachaichi.

### **Seminars**

- Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Facultat Economia i Empresa, Departament Economia Aplicada,
   "COVID-19 in European regions: Explaining disparities", 2022, Sébastien Bourdin, Mohamed
   Hachaichi.
- Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Facultat Economia i Empresa, Departament Economia Aplicada,
   "Territorial impacts of COVID-19 pandemic on EU regions", 2022, Sébastien Bourdin, Mohamed
   Hachaichi.

## Organization committee member in scientific workshops

- International colloquium organized by the Cities, Urban Planning, and Sustainable Development
  Laboratory at EPAU "Citizen and inhabitant participation in social and urban development: Between
  'good practices' and political slogan. Crossed views in the Algerian and international contexts",
  Algiers, 17-18 May 2017.
- Thematic day organized by the Ecole Polytechnique d'Architecture et d'Urbanisme (EPAU) "Use of new technologies of BIM in the process of documentation of the built environment", Algiers, 17-18 May 2017. Algerian Experiences" 06 Nov 2017.

### Reviewer

I'm a reviwer at the following journals:

Ecological Indicators Journal, Elsevier

• Environment, Development and Sustainability, Springer-nature

- Urban climate, Elsevier
- Water resources managment, Springer